{"tossups": [{"question": "This man caused the flight of the Oilliph\u00e9ist (ah-lahf-EYSHT), a monster who dug out the River Shannon. His goblet and bell comprise two of the \"precious minna.\" This man was forced to work as a shepherd in County Antrim after being abducted from England by slavers; after fleeing home, he returned to drive out the snakes and demonstrate the Trinity using a three-leafed  shamrock.  For  the  point,  name  this  evangelizer  and  patron  saint  of  Ireland.", "answer": "Saint <b><u>Patrick</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In what is now this country, the anarchist \"Free Territory\" was established by Nestor Makhno (MOCK-noh). This country was where tactics such as \"village sealing\" were used to enforce the Holdomor, an engineered famine punishing this country. This country's 2004 Orange Revolution failed to resolve disputes between its Euro-friendly West and pro-Russian East. For the point, name this country which, after Russia, is the most populous former Soviet state.", "answer": "<b><u>Ukraine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "At age twenty-four, this man was appointed head of the \"Radical Division,\" with responsibility for executing the Palmer Raids during the First Red Scare. This possible companion of Clyde Tolson coined the phrase \"public enemy number one\" for John Dillinger. He was rumored to have been blackmailed against admitting the existence of the Mafia. For the point, name this powerful head of the FBI until 1972.", "answer": "J. Edgar <b><u>Hoover</u></b> [John Edgar <b><u>Hoover</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Parts of this program were enforced using a quasi-military organization headed by Hugh Johnson which inspected shop windows for the \"blue eagle.\" This program was undermined by the Sick Chicken Case but partially upheld in <em>Wickard v. Filburn</em>; those cases addressed this program's National Recovery Act and Agricultural Adjustment Act components. For the point, name this sweeping agenda of economic stimulus that characterized Franklin Roosevelt's domestic policy.", "answer": "<b><u>New Deal</u></b> [or <b><u>National Recovery Act</u></b>, <b><u>National Recovery Administration</u></b>, or <b><u>NRA</u></b> until \"Wickard\" is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country's Young Congregation movement was a Christian dissenter circle which contributed to a failed 1953 uprising against its government. This country was led for almost its entire existence by Walter Ulbricht and Erich Honecker. Exit from this country was controlled by Checkpoint Charlie, the approved crossing of the Berlin Wall. For the point, name this country that no longer exists, having been re-absorbed into its capitalist neighbor in 1990.", "answer": "<b><u>East Germany</u></b> [or <b><u>GDR</u></b>; or <b><u>German Democratic Republic</u></b>; or <b><u>DDR</u></b>; or <b><u>Deutsche</u></b> <b><u>Demokratische Republik</u></b>; do not accept \"Germany\"]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Holders of this title comprise the \"Big Four\" of Najaf. The theory of velayat-e faqih (wah-LIE-et eh FAH-kee) says that people who hold this title are given absolute governance over men on Earth until the Hidden Imam returns. This title was held by a man who returned from exile in France in 1979 and oversaw the ten-year war with Iraq. For the point, give this title, held by the Supreme Leaders of Iran since the Islamic Revolution, including Ruhollah Khomeini.", "answer": "Grand <b><u>Ayatollah</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was attacked by the Whigs for his supposed extravagance in the Gold Spoon Oration. His re-election bid was denied by the \"log cabin and hard cider\" campaign. His administration bore the brunt of his predecessor's economic policies, such as the Specie Circular. The expression \"O.K.\" may derive from this man's nickname, Old Kinderhook. For the point, name this machine politician from New York who succeeded Andrew Jackson as President.", "answer": "Martin <b><u>van Buren</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The 1948 assassination of Jorge Eli\u00e9cer Gait\u00e1n (guy-TAHN) in this country sparked ten years of civil war between its Liberal and Conservative parties known as La Violencia. In the 1980s, this country was again wracked by violence among groups such as Cali and Medellin (med-ey-EEN), cartels which sought to dominate the cocaine trade which has long defined this country. For the point, name this country where FARC terrorists also challenge governments at Bogot\u00e1.", "answer": "<b><u>Colombia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1938, Owen Cash founded a society designed to preserve this kind of group, which uses a namesake seventh ringing chord. These groups arose in establishments that were the centers of American small-town life in the early 1900s and often wore boater hats. This kind of group can be seen at Disneyland as The Dapper Dans. For the point, identify this kind of group which sings Tin Pan Alley standards from the twentieth century, possibly to people getting a haircut.", "answer": "<b><u>barbershop quartet</u></b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "British painter Alfred Sisley used this style to depict the Thames. Louis Leroy derisively named this art movement after viewing an image of the harbor at Le Havre (loo-AHV-ruh). Pictures of people reading newspapers, drinking tea, or bathing their children were frequently executed in this style by Mary Cassatt. For the point, identify this French art movement named for a blurry depiction of a \"sunrise\" by Claude Monet.", "answer": "<b><u>impressionism</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The nobility of this country enjoyed the \"liberum (lee-BAIR-um) veto\" in the sjem (SAME), its perpetually gridlocked legislature. This country's succession war ended in 1738 following fracture on the death of Augustus the Strong. This country underwent three \"partitions\" in the eighteenth century and ceased to exist from 1794 to 1918, being mostly subsumed into Russia. For the point, name this eastern European state and frequent Russo-German battlefield.", "answer": "<b><u>Poland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was named in a five million dollar libel suit by Jimmy Connors arising from a dispute over the Davis Cup lineup. He defeated Connors in the final of Wimbledon in 1975, as he did Tom Okker and Dick Crealy in earlier instances of the U.S. Open and Australian Open; he is the only African-American to win any of the three events. For the point, name this tennis player who became the namesake of the U.S. Open venue following his death from AIDS in 1993.", "answer": "Arthur <b><u>Ashe</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The \"Semper Augustus\" and the \"viceroy\" were kinds of this item, whose trade led to the creation of the world's first futures market. During the height of interest in these items, a sailor was imprisoned for eating one worth a year's salary. These items lost 99 percent of their market value per month after their \"bubble\" crashed in 1637. For the point, what were these archetypal examples of an irrational economic \"mania,\" which briefly dominated the Dutch economy?", "answer": "<b><u>tulip</u></b> bulbs", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A trip down this river is chronicled in the book <em>Through the Dark Continent</em> by Henry Morton Stanley. The basin of this river is where the Force Publique operated, cutting off hands of people who did not meet rubber quotas for King Leopold. This river widens into the Malebo Pool, which separate Brazzaville from Kinshasa. For the point, identify this river of central Africa which lends its name to two countries on its shores.", "answer": "<b><u>Congo</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This god was believed to lead a court of forty-two judges. A tomb painting describing the Negative Confessions outlines this god's judgment, which could end with the soul being devoured by Ammit or uniting with the truth represented by Maat. This god weighed the dead's heart against a feather, according to the Book of the Dead. For the point, name this god who ruled the Egyptian underworld following his death at the hands of his brother Set.", "answer": "<b><u>Osiris</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The last major episode of this activity gave rise to the Donatist movement and took place under Diocletian. The main event in this activity was a request to make a token sacrifice to the emperor; those who refused might be killed by methods such as being forced to participate in gladiatorial contests with lions. For the point, identify this activity which intermittently arose following the reign of Nero and targeted a new religion in the Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>persecution of Christians</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "his kingdom was dominated by a noble class called the Junkers (YUNK-erz) and by the need to acquire men of at least 1.6 meters in height for its regiment of \"Potsdam giants.\" It was known as \"an army with a state\" under the rule of men such as Friedrich Wilhelm I and subsequent Hohenzollerns (HOH-ens-AH-lern) kings. For the point, name this militaristic north German state that became the basis of a unified Germany following a namesake war with France.", "answer": "<b><u>Prussia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "People who resisted the outcome of this battle included Hereward the Wake and Edgar the \u00c6theling. This battle's losers had just finished a march from their defeat of Harold Hardrada at Stamford Bridge, and were led by a man who suffered an arrow to the eye at this battle, Harold Godwinson. This battle is depicted on the Bayeux Tapestry. For the point, name this 1066 battle  at  which  William  the  Conqueror  established  Norman  supremacy  in  England.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Hastings</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This document was scheduled to be revised at the Annapolis Convention. The major law passed under this framework was the Northwest Ordinance. This document included an opt-in provision for Canada. Its major weaknesses were the lack of any tax power and requiring a unanimous vote to pass legislation. For the point, name this document under which the United  States  was  governed  prior  to  adoption  of  the  Constitution.", "answer": "<b><u>Articles of Confederation</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This scientist first proved that what were thought to be nebulae are more often distant galaxies. This man, who once held the Illinois high school high jump record, names a constant with units of inverse-time that can be used to determine the rate of expansion of the observable universe using his namesake law. For the point, name this American astronomer whose achievements were memorialized by giving his name to an orbiting space telescope.", "answer": "Edwin <b><u>Hubble</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "Warren Harding announced his intention to sign a bill against this practice, which was repeatedly filibustered in the early 1920s after being introduced by Leonidas Dyer. This practice was crusaded against in the book <em>A Red Record</em> by Ida B. Wells, and it often took place at the center of community picnics which issued postcards and other mementos. For the point, what was this form of mob violence used to intimidate blacks in segregated areas of the United States?", "answer": "<b><u>lynch</u></b>ing", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician's former deputy Maya Kodnan is serving a twenty-eight year prison sentence for involvement in the 2002 sectarian riots in Gujarat (GOO-juh-rot), where this man was chief minister for thirteen years. In 2014, his Bharatiya Janata (bah-rah-TEE-yuh jah-nuh-TAH) Party dislodged the Congress Party in general elections. For the point, name this newly elected Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "Narendra <b><u>Modi</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This scientist co-discovered a reciprocity law in photochemistry with Henry Roscoe. This man was given a container of mineral water from Durkheim which emitted a unique spectrum, leading him to first isolate cesium. To do so, he used the technique of spectral analysis which he and Gustav Kirchhoff had invented. For the point, name this chemist who collaborated with technician Peter Desaga on a safer device for heating chemical samples, his \"burner.\"", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Bunsen</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This woman kept an infamous blue dress from the Gap on the advice of Linda Tripp. This woman became the focus of an investigation originally chartered to investigate the Whitewater scandal, and is the subject of the quote \"I did not have sexual relations with that woman.\" For the point, name this intern whose affair with Bill Clinton led to Clinton's 1998 impeachment.", "answer": "Monica <b><u>Lewinsky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This performer retired from rock music for five years and entered the ministry after seeing the Sputnik satellite in the sky, which he believed was a sign from God. This man achieved success in the 1950s with \"Rip It Up\" and a song later covered by the Beatles, \"Lucille.\" For the point, name this rock and roll pioneer who was known for his extensive makeup and piano playing as well as for writing hits such as \"Tutti Frutti.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Little Richard</u></b> [or Richard Wayne <b><u>Penniman</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This duo allied with the Young Germany movement, causing King Ernest Augustus to fire them along with the rest of the G\u00f6ttingen Seven. This duo names a linguistic phenomenon in which voiceless stops became voiceless fricatives as Proto-Indo-European became Proto-Germanic. For the point, identify this pair of people who are most known for chronicling stories such as The Frog Prince, Hansel and Gretel, and Snow White in their namesake compendium of fairy tales.", "answer": "the Brothers <b><u>Grimm</u></b> [Jakob and Wilhelm <b><u>Grimm</u></b>]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {}, {"question": "This man was once yelled at by a peasant woman for letting her cakes burn while he was staying in the countryside in disguise. This man created some of the first translations of Christian literature into Old English, including Gregory the Great's <em>Pastoral Care</em> and Boethius's <em>Consolation of Philosophy</em>. This subject of a biography by Asser won the Battle of Edington to limit the scope of the Danelaw. For the point, name this \"great\" king of Wessex.", "answer": "<b><u>Alfred</u></b> the Great", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "References to this belief were obliterated by Horemheb, who wished to placate the priestly class that had been abandoned upon the construction of a new center of this belief at Amarna. According to a book by Sigmund Freud, this belief directly influenced Moses to found Judaism. For the point, identify this belief from the brief Egyptian religious revolution of Akhenaten, in which only the solar disc was worshipped to the exclusion of the rest of the pantheon.", "answer": "ancient Egyptian <b><u>monotheism</u></b> [or <b><u>Aten-worship</u></b> until \"Akhenaten\" is read]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This religious group promoted the Food for Life movement, which involves both preaching vegetarianism and providing food directly to the poor. This movement was founded in 1968 by Swami Prabhupada and became the subject of frequent legal battles in the 1970s over their aggressive proselytization and soliciting of donations in public spaces. For the point, name this Hindu offshoot practiced by bald, orange-robed missionaries who chant to a namesake god.", "answer": "<b><u>Hare Krishna</u></b> [or <b><u>International Society for Krishna Consciousness</u></b>; or <b><u>ISKCON</u></b>]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "During voyages east, this country colonized Daman and Diu, which, along with Goa, it held onto until the twentieth century. This country was granted everything east of an Atlantic meridian by Pope Alexander VI in the Treaty of Tordesillas (TOR-duh-SEE-yahs). This country colonized Cape Verde, the Azores, and Brazil. For the point, name this country for which Pedro Cabral, Bartolomeo Dias, and Vasco da Gama sailed.", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle was made possible by blocking a join-up with George Crook at the Battle of the Rosebud. A non-participant in this battle had a vision of \"grasshoppers falling from the sky\" prior to its start. Survivors of this battle included the horse Comanche. This battle was a victory for Chief Gall and Crazy Horse against the 7th Cavalry. For the point, name this 1876 clash in  Montana  which  destroyed  the  army  of  George  Armstrong  Custer.", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Little Bighorn</u></b> [or <b><u>Custer's Last Stand</u></b> until \"Custer\" is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1765, the New York state assembly was obliged to pay the cost of this process at the request of Thomas Gage. In 1774, this process was mandated upon private homeowners as part of the Intolerable Acts. Colonial anger at this process led to the Third Amendment being included in the Constitution. For the point, identify this British practice in which redcoats were given room and board by force in their area of operation.", "answer": "<b><u>quartering</u></b> of soldiers", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This empire was founded after the spur from a rooster's leg was used to defeat Sumanguru at the Battle of Kirina. This empire, whose foundation myth is contained in the Epic of Sundiata, declined after the fall of Mima and other holdings to the ascendant Songhai. For the point, name this West African empire which reached its greatest height under a man who lavishly gave away gold during his pilgrimage to Mecca, Mansa Musa.", "answer": "<b><u>Mali</u></b> empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman was criticized for accepting a decoration from Haitian dictator Jean-Claude Duvalier and for campaigning against abortion legalization in Ireland in Christopher Hitchens's polemic <em>The Missionary Position</em>. The Kalighat Home for the Dying was the center of her Missionaries of Charity organization, which focused mainly on hospice care. For the point, name this Albanian-born Catholic \"religious sister\" who became famous for her work in India.", "answer": "<b><u>Mother Teresa</u></b> [or Anjez\u00eb Gonxhe <b><u>Bojaxhiu</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This artist is frequently accused of portraying members of a local historical society as cross-dressers in his satirical <em>Daughters of Revolution</em>. He portrayed a man pulling back a curtain to reveal an adult-faced George Washington as a child, holding a hatchet, in <em>Parson Weems' Fable</em>. For the point, name this American painter who used a local dentist and his own sister as the model for the pitchfork-holding Iowa farm couple in <em>American Gothic.</em>", "answer": "Grant <b><u>Wood</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man used a racemic mixture of tartaric acid to first demonstrate the chemical principle of chirality (kai-RAA-lit-ee). Working with Emile Roux (ROO), this scientist successfully treated nine-year-old Joseph Meister, who had been bitten by a dog, with his new rabies vaccine. For the point, name this French scientist and \"father of microbiology,\" who invented a method for sterilizing alcohol and milk now known by his name.", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Pasteur</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This case reached the Supreme Court after a longstanding doctrine of treating the topic as moot was rescinded, and it relied on a right established in <em>Griswold v. Connecticut</em>. Before deciding this case, Justice Blackmun did extensive research at the Mayo Clinic. This case was paired with <em>Doe v. Bolton</em> and ruled in favor of Norma McCorvey, who later became a pro-life activist. For the point, name this 1973 Supreme Court case that legalized most abortions.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Roe</u></b> v. Wade</em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people were held responsible for breaking into the king's bedchamber during the Affair of the Placards. These people had strongholds at Mountauban and La Rochelle, and they were protected in a document which metaphorically \"crucified\" Pope Clement VII. For the point, name these people who were granted toleration by the Edicts of Nantes (NONT) and were  followers  of  John  Calvin  who  comprised  the  bulk  of  French  Protestants.", "answer": "<b><u>Huguenot</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>Protestant</u></b>s until it is read; prompt on <b><u>Calvinist</u></b>s until \"Calvin\" is read]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man attracted national notoriety after murdering John Sheets. This man previously took part in the Centralia Massacre as part of a Confederate-allied Bushwacker militia. He allied with Frank Younger throughout the 1870s until an attempted crime in Northfield, Minnesota went awry. He was later killed for reward money by his associate Robert Ford. For the point, name this leader of a notorious outlaw gang which focused on bank robbery.", "answer": "Jesse <b><u>James</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city is the namesake of a document prepared by Philipp Melanchthon (meh-LANK-thun) which was one of the first creeds of the Reformation. A meeting at this city in 1555 gave formal put forth the principle of \"cuius regio, eius religio\" (COO-ee-uss REH-gee-oh EY-uss reh-LIG-ee-oh). For the point, name this city whose \"peace\" allowed princes within the Holy Roman Empire to choose either Lutheranism or Catholicism for their territories.", "answer": "<b><u>Augsburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was alleged to have the ability to detach and replace his head in the scandalmongering <em>Secret History</em> written by his courtier Procopius (pruh-COPE-ee-uss). This emperor employed the generals Narses and Belisarius, who suppressed a riot at a chariot race that grew into the Nika Revolt. For the point, name this husband of Theodora who codified Roman law and was the \"great\" ruler of the Byzantine Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Justinian</u></b> I [or <b><u>Justinian</u></b> the Great]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man's visit to the White House is the subject of the lost Scott Joplin opera <em>A Guest of</em> <em>Honor</em>; his dining with Theodore Roosevelt sparked the ire of Southern Congressmen. This man advised his followers to \"cast down your bucket where you are\" and was the longtime leader of the Tuskegee Institute. For the point, name this formulator of the Atlanta Compromise who rivaled W.E.B. DuBois (doo-BOYZ) for leadership of the 1900s black community.", "answer": "Booker T. <b><u>Washington</u></b> [Booker Taliaferro <b><u>Washington</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Umayyad (oo-MY-ud) Dynasty promulgated an order to curse this man at every prayer service. This man's son Husayn was martyred in an event remembered on the holiday of Ashura (AH-shuh-ruh). This man was the last of the Rashidun, or rightly guided caliphs. For the point, name this man whose original attempt to succeed Muhammad gave rise to a movement later known as Shiism, which holds him to be the first imam.", "answer": "<b><u>Ali</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "These objects were the subject of the \"kipper und wipper\" phenomenon in the 1620s, and a satire on a plan for these objects was put forth in the <em>Drapier's Letters</em> of Jonathan Swift. Isaac Newton was appointed the royal \"master\" of a facility for making these objects, whose composition was the subject of Gresham's Law. For the point, name these things which could be \"clipped\" or \"debased\" and are a metallic store of value studied by numismatists.", "answer": "<b><u>coin</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Cornelius Nepos wrote the earliest surviving examples of this genre. The historian Tacitus ventured into this genre in his book <em>Agricola</em>, as did Xenophon (ZEE-nuh-fahn) in his <em>Cyropedia.</em> A major practitioner of this genre put Roman and Greek subjects next to each other to draw comparative conclusions. For the point, name this genre which Plutarch wrote in the <em>Parallel Lives</em>, which outlines the life stories of Sulla, Cicero, and others.", "answer": "<b><u>biography</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man' government is currently opposed by the New Citizens Movement. This man formed a body that promises \"comprehensive deepening reforms.\" He translated the title of a Thomas Friedman column to name his political platform, which was also informed by his time in 1985 living in Muscatine, Iowa as the guest of an American family. For the point, name this \"Chinese Dream\" advocate who, in 2012, succeeded Hu Jintao as president of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Xi</u></b> (\"she\") Jinping", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This company made half a billion dollars selling off Maidstone in 2010, nine years after centralizing its manufacturing in Brantford. It is named for the NHL defenseman who founded it in 1964. This company, which was formerly merged with Wendy's, was bought out by Burger King in August 2010. Its iconic \"roll up the rim\" promotion will continue. For the point, name this donut shop which is a fixture in Canada.", "answer": "<b><u>Tim Horton</u></b>'s", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man briefly attempted to live as an itinerant farmhand after falling in love with Bea Kozera, but quit after he realized he could not keep up with the pace of picking cotton at $1.50 per day. Bea is fictionalized as \"Terry\" and this author as \"Sal Paradise\" in his novel about the experience. For the point, name this Beat Generation author of the travelogue <em>On the Road.</em>", "answer": "Jack <b><u>Kerouac</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This event created formations of lava-like material known as corium. This event created the Red Forest by killing pine trees. As a result of this event, the Zone of Alienation was established around Pripyat. This event was publicized after detectors in Sweden noticed it. It was caused by an improperly contained power surge and led to about three thousand deaths. For the point, name this 1986 event in Ukraine, the first-ever \"Level 7\" nuclear disaster.", "answer": "<b><u>Chernobyl</u></b> accident", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Payment for members of this body was a plank of the Chartist movement. This body's composition was radically altered by the elimination of \"rotten boroughs\" and \"pocket boroughs\" in the Great Reform Bill. The People's Budget crisis led to the effective end of the veto over this body held by the House of Lords. For the point, name this lower and more important house of the British Parliament.", "answer": "British House of <b><u>Commons</u></b> [or <b><u>Parliament</u></b> until \"Lords\" is read]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man declined an offer to serve as George Wallace's running mate, sixteen years after he starred in the anti-Communist film <em>Big Jim McLain</em>. He portrayed Genghis Khan in 1956's <em>The</em> <em>Conqueror</em>, which was filmed near a nuclear test site and may have given him fatal cancer. For 10 points, name this star of <em>Stagecoach</em>, <em>The Searchers</em>, and <em>Rio Bravo</em> among other Westerns.", "answer": "John <b><u>Wayne</u></b> [or Marion <b><u>Morrison</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This group is sometimes named for its co-leader, James Reed, who was expelled from this group after stabbing John Snyder to death. This group was near Bear Valley when the \"Forlorn Hope\" faction separated. This group waited until too late in the year to take the Hastings Cutoff, leading to them being snowed in atop the Sierra Nevadas in 1846. For the point, name this ill-fated group of migrants to California who engaged in cannibalism while starving.", "answer": "<b><u>Donner Party</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Seven months prior to this event, its perpetrator had attempted a similar action against General Edwin Walker. Following this event, policeman J. D. Tippit was killed. Governor John Connally was wounded during this event, which was captured on the Zapruder film and took place at Dealey Plaza in front of the Texas School Book Depository. For the point, identify this November 1963 event carried out by Lee Harvey Oswald.", "answer": "<b><u>assassination</u></b> of <b><u>J</u></b>ohn F. <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> [or <b><u>assassination of JFK</u></b>; prompt on answers that do not give a first name or initial, so as to distinguish from Robert Kennedy]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man, who died after ingesting mercury from quacks offering eternal life, ordered the \"burning of books and burying of scholars\" to implement the governance policies of Han Feizi (<b>pr. FAI-zee</b>). This man's armies conquered states such as Han, Wei, and Chu to subsume all of China to his rule by 221 BC. For the point, name this autocratic emperor who ended the Warring States Period by forming the brief Qin (<b>pr. CHIN</b>) Dynasty.", "answer": "Qin <b><u>Shi Huang</u></b>di", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Researchers in this field of study performed the \"kerplunk\" experiments and designed a device involving a sheet of transparent glass called the \"visual cliff.\" Wilhelm Wundt opened the first laboratory dedicated to experiments in this field. Early writers in this field included Alfred Adler and the theorizer of archetypes, Carl Jung (YUNG). For the point, name this field of social science in which behaviorists and Freudians work.", "answer": "<b><u>psychology</u></b> [do not accept \"psychiatry\"]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "This character is constantly asked by Dutch traders whether he stepped on a crucifix in order to be allowed entrance to Japan. Shortly thereafter, he finds a land where men are slaves to horses called Houyhnhnms (WIN-ims). He earlier contended with giants in Brobdingnag (BRAHB-ding-nag) and tiny people in Lilliput (LIL-uh-put). For the point, name this character who satirizes eighteenth-century English society with his \"travels\" in a Jonathan Swift novel.", "answer": "Lemuel <b><u>Gulliver</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "A failed attempt at proclaiming this status occurred in the 10th of October Manifesto. This status was the goal of the Ten Years War and the Little War, and many people were converted to this objective following the atrocities of \"Butcher\" Weyler. This status was guaranteed by the U.S.'s Teller Amendment but undermined in practice by the later Platt Amendment. Jose Marti was the poet of this cause. For the point, identify this movement to expel Spain from a Caribbean island.", "answer": "<b><u>Cuban independence</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The speech which popularized this expression was called \"The Sinews of Peace.\" This phrase was originally coined by Joseph Goebbels, but it was popularized in a speech at Westminster College, which claims that it extended \"from Stettin on the Baltic to Trieste on the Adriatic.\" For the point, give this phrase which was introduced to the world at large in 1946 by Winston Churchill, and described the impenetrable barrier between Western and Eastern Europe.", "answer": "\"<b><u>iron curtain</u></b>\"", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After being accused of not knowing what having a job was like by Howard Metzenbaum, this man gave the strident \"Gold Star Mothers Speech,\" securing his nomination to the Senate from Ohio. His Presidential ambitions were derailed by a fall in his bathtub. For the point, name this astronaut whose 1962 mission in the <em>Friendship 7</em> made him the first American to orbit the Earth.", "answer": "John <b><u>Glenn</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This law was entirely unenforceable in the Lake Champlain region, which consequently became a hotbed for smuggling. A cartoon satirizing this law shows a man holding a barrel of flour being bitten by a turtle named \"Ograbme\" (oh-GRAB-me). This law was replaced by the milder Non-Intercourse Act. For the point, name this 1807 attempt to punish Britain and France for attacks on American ships by banning all foreign trade at U.S. ports.", "answer": "<b><u>Embargo</u></b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This king ordered the construction of the initially disastrous central hospital, the Allgemeines Krankenhaus (AHL-geh-MY-niss KRON-ken-HOWS). The language of education changed from Latin to German under this monarch. This king issued the Robot Patent freeing serfs, and the Patent of Toleration which extended liberties to Protestants and Jews. For the point, name this last great Holy Roman Emperor, the son of Maria Theresa who reigned from 1765 to 1790.", "answer": "<b><u>Joseph II</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Joseph</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A plan to enroll these people in the British Army sparked the Gordon Riots. These people's \"emancipation\" was resisted by the Duke of Wellington but finally achieved due to the efforts of Daniel O'Connell. Tony Blair became one of these people after leaving the Prime Ministry. These people used \"priest-holes\" when they were persecuted and were briefly re-ascendant under Bloody Mary. For the point, name this group, the largest minority religion in England.", "answer": "English Roman <b><u>Catholic</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man sent an August 2014 note to the Koyasan Okuno-in (koh-yoh-SAHN oh-koo-NOH-en) monastery, which caused similar controversy as his December 2013 visit to the Yasukuni (yah-soo-KOO-nee) shrine. Both efforts were part of his attempts to rehabilitate World War II war criminals, which China and South Korea oppose. For the point, name this Liberal Democratic Party leader, the current prime minister of Japan.", "answer": "Shinzo <b><u>Abe</u></b> (AH-bay)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This event was triggered by a speech which accused a Senator of taking \"a mistress to whom he has made his vows, and who, though ugly to others, is always lovely to him.\" It happened after Andrew Butler was called out in the \"Crime Against Kansas\" speech for loving \"the harlot, slavery.\" For the point, identify this 1856 event in which a U.S. Representative invaded the Senate chamber to beat a Senator with a cane.", "answer": "<b><u>Brooks-Sumner</u></b> incident", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the interwar period, this country was threatened by the fascist Arrow Cross Party and was governed by the \"regent\" Miklos Horthy (HOR-tee). This country's privileges were recognized in the Ausgleich (OWS-glike) following the agitation of Lajos Kossuth (LYE-osh kow-SOOT) and the creation of the Dual Monarchy. For the point, name this country which became an equal partner in the last phase of the Hapsburg Empire alongside Austria.", "answer": "<b><u>Hungary</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Antics during the trial of this group included flying a Viet Cong flag from their defense table and summoning Judy Collins to sing a song as a witness. These defendants antagonized Judge Julius Hoffman, who was not related to the man who became their most notorious member following the severing of Bobby Seale's trial. For the point, name this group of activists which underwent a highly publicized trial following their disruption of the 1968 Democratic National Convention.", "answer": "<b><u>Chicago Seven</u></b> [or <b><u>Chicago Eight</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man fled from Northampton Castle after being convicted of treason for refusing to sign the Constitutions of Clarendon. This man's tomb is the destination of the pilgrims in <em>The</em> <em>Canterbury Tales</em>, and his death is the subject of T.S. Eliot's play <em>Murder in the Cathedral</em>. He was killed after a king slyly lamented \"will no one rid me of this troublesome priest?\" For the point, name this Archbishop who was assassinated by knights of Henry II in 1170.", "answer": "Thomas \u00e0 <b><u>Becket</u></b> [or Thomas <b><u>Becket</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the year prior to this war, an airstrike on Al-Samu and false Soviet intelligence reports about a planned invasion caused paranoia, leading to a closure of the Gulf of Aqaba and a blockade of Elat. This war resulted in the annexation of the Sinai Peninsula, which was returned, as well as the Golan Heights, Gaza Strip, and West Bank. For the point, identify this 1967 war between Israel and a pan-Arab coalition, which was named for its unusually short duration.", "answer": "<b><u>Six-Day</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of these people became emperor and set up a system of copper boxes into which anonymous denunciations of traitors could be placed. Another of these people was a notorious member of the Gang of Four who took offense at an opera and began the Cultural Revolution. These people included Wu, Jiang Qing (CHING), and the warrior Mulan. For the point, name these people who underwent \"foot-binding\" and comprise about half the population of China.", "answer": "Chinese <b><u>women</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}